<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<advantages>
    
    <advantage>
        <name>Absolute Direction</name>
        <points>5</points>
        <description>You always know which way is north, and you can always 
            retrace a path you have followed within the past month, no matter
            how faint or confusing it may be. This ability does not work in
            environments such as interstellar space, the limbo of the astral
            plane, etc., but it does work underground, underwater, and on other
            planets. Also gives a +3 bonus on your Navigator skill. 
        </description>
    </advantage>
    
    <advantage>
        <name>Absolute Timing</name>
        <points>5</points>
        <description>You have an accurate mental clock. Unless you have been 
            knocked unconscious, hypnotized, or otherwise interfered with, you 
            always know what time it is, down to the second. You can also 
            measure any elapsed time with equal accuracy. Sleep does not 
            interfere with this (and you can wake up at a predetermined time if 
            you choose). Changes of time zone also have no effect. Time travel 
            will confuse you until you find out what the "new" time is. 
        </description>
    </advantage>
 
    <advantage>
        <name>Acute Hearing</name>
        <points>2 points/level</points>
        <description>You get a bonus on your Hearing roll (see p.  92) whenever you 
            must roll to hear something, or when the GM rolls against IQ to see if 
            you noticed a sound. Cost: 2 points for every +1 bonus to your roll.  
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Acute Taste and Smell</name>
        <points>2 points/level</points>
        <description>You get a bonus on any Taste or Smell roll (see p. 92). For
            instance, the GM might roll to see if you noticed the taste or smell of
            poison in your drink. Cost: 2 points for every +1 bonus to your roll.  
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Acute Vision</name>
        <points>2 points/level</points>
        <description>You get a bonus on any Vision roll  - that is, when you roll to 
            look for something, or whenever the GM rolls against IQ to see if 
            you noticed something. Cost: 2 points for every +1 bonus to your 
            roll.  
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Alertness</name>
        <points>5 points/level</points>
        <description>A general bonus you get on  any Sense roll, or when the GM 
            rolls against your IQ to see if you notice something. This advantage 
            can  be combined with any or all of the acute senses. Cost: 5 points 
            for each +1 bonus to your roll.  
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Ambidexterity</name>
        <points>10</points>
        <description>You can use both hands with equal skill. You do not suffer the -
            4 DX penalty for using an "offhand" (see  Handedness,  p. 13), and 
            can fight (or act) with either hand, or (in an All-Out Attack) with 
            both hands at once. Should some accident befall one of your arms or 
            hands, assume it is the left one. 
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Animal Empathy</name>
        <points>5</points>
        <description>You understand animals and like them, and they like you. You 
            get a +2 on any reaction roll by a wild animal, and a +4 on any 
            reaction from a tame animal. You also get a +4 bonus on any "ani -
            mal" skill roll (Animal Handling, Riding, Vet, etc.). However, you 
            may never kill an animal without a very good reason,  and you 
            should try to prevent others from doing so. Note that killing for food 
            is perfectly  acceptable,  and in a hunt ing situation you will get a  +3 bonus 
            to find game. 
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Charisma</name>
        <points>5 points/level</points>
        <description>This is the natural ability to impress and lead others. Anyone 
            can acquire a semblance of charisma by good looks, good manners 
            and intelligence  - but real charisma works independently of these 
            things, and you either have it or you don't. It affects any reaction 
            roll made by any intelligent creature. Cost: 5 points for each +1 
            bonus.
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Clerical Investment</name>
        <points>5 or more points, GM's discretion</points>
        <description>You have been ordained as a minister of some religion. A cleric 
            has a number of powers and privileges that a layman lacks, including 
            a +1 reaction bonus from co-religionists and those who respect his 
            faith. He or she will be addressed by a title  - Father, Sister, 
            Reverend, Shaman  - and can perform  such ceremonies as 
            Confirmation, Marriage and Exorcism. 
            Remember that not all clerics are nuns or rabbis. Aka'Ar, high 
            priest of the unholy Cult of Set, is a vested priest as well, and the 
            blessings and marriages he performs will be just as meaningful to 
            his own flock as are those of a vicar to his parish. And, if Set so 
            wills, Aka'Ar will be able to perform exorcisms as potent as those 
            of a Christian minister, if not more so. Aka'Ar will have a better 
            working knowledge of demons . . .  
            The GM should determine whether clerics, in his campaign, can 
            call upon active aid from Beyond. If so, and if clerics are  known to 
            be able to get such aid, Clerical Investment will be worth 10 points or 
            more. If Investment is merely (as far as the players know) a 
            "social" advantage, it costs 5 points.  
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Combat Reflexes</name>
        <points>15</points>
        <description>You have extraordinary reactions and are very rarely surprised 
            for more than a moment. You get a +1 to any Active Defense in 
            combat. You also get a +1 on any Fast-Draw skill, and +2 to any 
            Fright Check (p. 93). And you never "freeze" (see p. 122). 
            Furthermore, your  side  gets +1 on initiative rolls to avoid a sur-
            prise attack, or +2 if you are the leader. You, personally, get a +6 on 
            any IQ roll to wake up or to recover from surprise or a mental "stun." 
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Common Sense</name>
        <points>10</points>
        <description>Any time you start to do something that the GM feels is STUPID, 
            he rolls against your IQ. A successful roll means he must warn you, 
            "Hadn't you better think about that?" This advantage allows an 
            impulsive player to take the part of a thoughtful character. 
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Danger Sense</name>
        <points>15</points>
        <description>You can't depend on it, but sometimes you get this prickly feeling
            right at the back of your neck, and you know something's wrong
            ...  If you have Danger Sense, the GM rolls once against your IQ
            secretly, in any situation involving an ambush, impending disaster, or
            similar hazard. A successful roll means you get a warning that
            something's wrong. A roll of 3 or 4 means you get a little detail as to
            the nature of the danger. 
            Note: In a campaign that uses psi powers, this can be an ESP
            ability! See Psionics, Chapter 20. 
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Double-Jointed</name>
        <points>5</points>
        <description>Your body is unusually flexible. You have a +3 on any Climbing 
            roll, on any roll to escape from ropes, handcuffs or other restraints, or 
            on any Mechanic roll (to reach into an engine, of course!). 
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Eidetic Memory</name>
        <points>30/60 points</points>
        <description>You remember everything you see or hear. This talent comes in 
            two levels. 
            At the first level, you remember the general sense of everything 
            you concentrate on. Thus, all points you put into "regular" mental 
            skills count double (there is no bonus for psi skills). You get a +1 on 
            magic spells. Also: whenever you need to remember a detail of 
            something you have been told, the GM rolls against your IQ. A suc-
            cessful roll means he must give you the information! Cost: 30 points. 
            The second level is true "photographic memory." You remember 
            everything that has ever happened to you! All points you put into 
            "regular" mental skills count  quadruple.  You get a +2 bonus  on 
            magic spells. Furthermore, any time you (as the  player)  forget a 
            detail your character has seen or heard, the GM or other players 
            must remind you - truthfully! Cost: 60 points. 
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Empathy</name>
        <points>15</points>
        <description>You have a "feeling" for people. When you first meet someone, or 
            when you are reunited after an absence, you may request the GM  to 
            roll against your IQ. He will then tell you what you "feel" about that 
            person. (Note that a failed roll means the GM may lie to you.) This 
            talent, when it works, is excellent for spotting imposters, ghostly 
            possession, etc., and determining the true loyalties of NPCs. You 
            can also use i t to determine whether someone is  lying . . . not what 
            the truth really is, but just whether they are being honest with you. 
            Note: In a campaign that uses psi powers, this can be a Psi ability! 
            See Psionics, Chapter 20. 
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>High Pain Threshold</name>
        <points>10</points>
        <description>You a re as susceptible to injury as anyone else, but you don't feel 
            it as much. If you are hurt in combat, you are not stunned and do not 
            have the normal DX penalty on your next turn (exception: a  head 
            blow or critical hit will still stun you). If you are tortured physically, 
            you are at a +3 to resist. The GM may let you roll at  Will +3 to 
            ignore pain in other situations. 
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Immunity to disease</name>
        <points>10</points>
        <description>Your body naturally resists all disease organisms. You will never 
            catch any infection or disease "naturally." If you are forcibly injected 
            with a disease organism, your body will throw it off immediately. 
            Virus and fungus invasions are also considered "disease," though 
            larger parasites (e.g., a tapeworm) are not. You may not  take this 
            advantage unless you also start with a HT of 12 or better. However, 
            the immunity will remain, even if HT is reduced below 12.  
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Intuition</name>
        <points>15</points>
        <description>You usually guess right. When you are faced with a number of 
            alternatives, and no logical way to choose between them, you can 
            use your intuition as follows: The GM adds your IQ to the number 
            of "right" choices, subtracts the number of possible "wrong" 
            choices, and rolls against the resulting number. A successful roll 
            means he steers you to a good choice; a roll of 3 or 4 means he 
            tells you the  best  choice. A failed roll means you are given no 
            information. A critical failure means he steers you toward a bad 
            choice . . . your intuition failed you. The GM can modify this system 
            as he sees fit for other situations in which intuition might logi cally 
            help.  
            Only one roll per question is allowed. Note also: The GM cannot 
            let this advantage be used to short-circuit adventures - by let ting the 
            intuitive detective walk into a room, slap the cuffs on the  guilty 
            party, and close the case. At the most, intuition would point the 
            detective in the direction of a good clue. GMs who  don't think 
            they can control this advantage should not allow it at all.  
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Language Talent</name>
        <points>2 points/level</points>
        <description>You pick up languages quickly. This talent  is  cumulative with 
            others; if you have Eidetic Memory and Language Talent, you will 
            probably be speaking 20 languages before long. Whenever you 
            learn any language, add your level of Language Talent to your IQ. 
            Example: Your IQ is 10; your Language Talent is 2. You learn lan-
            guages as though your IQ were 12! You get the same bonus on 
            Linguistics skill. See  Language Skills, p. 54. Cost: 2 points for each + 
            1 bonus.  
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Legal Enforcement Powers</name>
        <points>5, 10 or 15 points</points>
        <description>You are an officer of the law, with all the accompanying rights, 
            powers and restr ictions. In some times and places, this amounts to a 
            license to kill; in others, it's little more than the right to carry a 
            badge and write parking tickets. 
            The point cost is determined by the rights and privileges of the 
            character's branch of law enforcement. Generally, a policeman with 
            local jurisdiction, the ability to arrest suspected criminals, the right to 
            perform searches with an appropriate warrant, and  possibly  the 
            right to carry a concealed weapon, has 5 points' worth of Legal 
            Enforcement Powers.  Examples would be a Victorian bobby or a 
            modern policeman. 
            Someone with national or international jurisdiction, or not obligated 
            to respect the civil rights of others,  or  free to engage in covert 
            investigations,  or  able to kill with relative impunity, must pay 10 
            points for his powers. Examples would be a modern FBI agent or a 
            medieval Royal Guardsman. 
            An officer with three or more of the above abilities has 15 points of 
            Legal Enforcement Powers. An example might be a top agent of  the 
            CIA, KGB, or MI -5. 
            Legal Enforcement Powers usually go hand-in-hand with an 
            appropriate Duty disadvantage, and with a Reputation which may be 
            an advantage, a disadvantage, or both. 
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Lightning Calculator</name>
        <points>5</points>
        <description>You have the ability to do math in your head, instantly. If you 
            have this talent, then you (the  player) may use a calculator at any 
            time, to figure anything you want - even if your character is fleeing 
            for his life at the time! Alternatively, for simple math problems, the 
            GM may just say the character knows the answer. 
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Literacy</name>
        <points>0 or 10 points</points>
        <description>Although in real life this is a skill, it is treated as an advantage 
            for reasons which are explained on p. 17. In general, you are 
            assumed to be literate if your world is mostly literate, and illiterate if 
            your world is mostly illiterate (TL4 and below). Being literate in  a 
            world where most people cannot read is an advantage worth 10 
            points. Being illiterate in a world where most people can read is a 
            disadvantage, worth -10 points. 
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Longevity</name>
        <points>5</points>
        <description>Your lifespan is naturally very long. You will fail aging rolls 
            (see p. 83) only on a natural 17 or 18. A character with this advantage 
            gets no points by taking Age as a disadvantage! 
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Luck</name>
        <points>15 or 30 points</points>
        <description>Some people are just born lucky. Once per every hour of  play, 
            you may make up to three rolls for some one thing, and then take 
            the best one! If the GM is rolling (e.g., to see whether a certain 
            NPC arrives, or to see if you notice something), you tell him you 
            are using your luck, and he must roll three times and give you the 
            best result. You can use this advantage after the dice are rolled the 
            first time to get two more attempts. Cost: 15 points. 
            Extraordinary Luck works the same way, but it is usable every 
            30 minutes, instead of every hour. Cost: 30 points. 
            Your luck only applies on rolls for your character to try to do 
            something, OR on outside events that affect you or your whole 
            party, OR when you are being attacked (in which case you may 
            Bake the attacker roll three times and take the worst roll!). 
            Luck cannot be shared. If Strong Sam is trying to kick open a door, 
            Lucky Lou can't stand behind him and transfer his luck. He'll 
            have to kick that door himself. 
            Once you use your Luck, you must wait an hour (or 30 minutes 
            for Extraordinary Luck) before using it again. You cannot use Luck at 
            11:58, and then again at 12:01. Note also that Luck cannot be saved 
            up. You cannot play for hours without using Luck and then  use it 
            several times in a row! 
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Magical Aptitude (Magery)</name>
        <points>5 points for first level, 10 points/level afterward</points>
        <description>You have a bonus to learn any magic spell. Of course, if you are 
            from a non-magical culture you will not start with any spells, but 
            you can still learn them more easily if you ever find an opportunity. 
            And when you enter a magical world, those who can detect your 
            aura (p. 162) will recognize you as a potentially powerful, though 
            untrained, magic-user. They may want to teach you - or kill you. 
            When you learn any spell, you learn it as though your IQ were 
            equal to (IQ + aptitude).  Example:  You have an IQ of 14 and a  
            Magical Aptitude of 3. You learn spells as though your IQ was 17! 
            In addition, the GM will roll vs. your (IQ + aptitude) when you 
            first see any magic object, and again when you first  touch  it. If the 
            roll succeeds, you will know intuitively that it is magical. A roll of 3 
            or 4 will also tell you whether the magic is helpful or dangerous, and 
            about how strong it is.  Example:  If you have IQ 13 and 3 levels  of 
            aptitude, you will recognize a magic item on a 16 or less. If the  GM 
            misses the roll, he will simply tell you nothing. Note that use of this 
            advantage becomes tricky for a character from a non-magical 
            background - like 20th-century Earth. Such a character will still have 
            the ability to sense magic, though until he gains experience with 
            magic the GM should not say, "That idol is magical," but "That idol 
            looks very strange to you, very sinister. You sense there is something 
            special about it." Characters without Magical Aptitude don't get  any 
            roll to sense magical objects. 
            Cost: 15 points for the first level of Magery; 10 points for each 
            subsequent level up to a maximum of 3 levels. 
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
        <points>2 points/level</points>
        <description>You are less likely to be affected by magic of most kinds. Note 
            that this advantage  cannot  be combined with Magical Aptitude. 
            You cannot be both magically apt and magically resistant. Indeed,  if 
            you have Magic Resistance, you can't cast spells at all (though  you 
            can still use magic weapons). Also, you cannot "turn it off to  let 
            friendly spells be cast on you. 
            Magic Resistance, and its precise level, can be recognized by 
            any mage who looks at your aura, or by anyone who casts a spell 
            against you. The level of your Magic Resistance is subtracted from 
            the caster's skill with the spell. If you have a Magic Resistance of  3, 
            and the caster has skill 15,  his effective skill is 12. Magic 
            Resistance also adds to resistance against elixirs (see  GURPS 
            Magic, pp. 98-100). 
            Your Magic Resistance also adds to your ordinary resistance 
            against spells that can be resisted. 
            Your Magic Resistance thus protects you from having a spell 
            thrown directly on you. It does not defend you against (a) missile 
            spells; (b) attacks by magical weapons; (c) information-gathering
            spells in which the spell is not thrown directly on you, like Aura. 
            Magic Resistance has no effect on psionic attacks. 
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Mathematical Ability</name>
        <points>10</points>
        <description>This gives you a +3 on any math or computer skill except Computer 
            Operation, and a +2 to any Engineering skill at Tech Level 6+.  
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Military Rank</name>
        <points>5 points/level of rank</points>
        <description>Just as Status (p. 16) reflects your position in society, Military 
            Rank (also called "grade") reflects your position in a military or 
            paramilitary organization. Each rank has authority over those of 
            lower ranks - regardless of personal ability. Cost: 5 points per rank, up 
            to Rank 8. 
            Titles of ranks vary between organizations. Typical examples:  
            Rank 8: Corps-level command or higher (Lieutenant General,  
            General or Admiral) 
            Rank 7: Division-level command (Brigadier or Major General) Rank 
            6: Brigade/group/regimental command (Colonel) or Captain 
            of a capital ship 
            Rank 5: Battalion command (Lieutenant Colonel) Rank 4: Company 
            command (Captain or Major) Rank 3: Platoon command (Lieutenant or 
            Warrant Officer) Rank 2: Non-commissioned officer (NCO) 
            associated with platoon, 
            company, or battalion commands (Sergeant 1st Class, First 
            Sergeant or Sergeant-Major) 
            Rank 1: Squad/platoon NCO (Sergeant or Staff Sergeant) Rank 0: 
            Enlisted man (Private, Airman or Ordinary Seaman) 
            In good professional armies, field-grade officers (Rank 5 or 6) 
            must have a Leadership skill of at least 12; general officers (Rank 
            7+) must have a Leadership skill of at least 13. This prerequisite 
            can be satisfied by its default of ST-5. Incompetence in the higher 
            ranks is not tolerated under any circumstances. (But in many less-
            professional or politically-dominated forces, incompetent officers 
            are common.)  
            It is strongly recommended that no PC be allowed to start the 
            game with a Military Rank above 5, since high rank is normally 
            bestowed only on leaders of proven ability.  
            Military Rank, unlike social status, costs no money to maintain. 
            But insubordination, extreme cowardice, or stupidity can cause a 
            permanent or temporary loss in rank, depending upon your superior's 
            reaction (as played by the GM). 
            Brevet ranks are given by superior officers (usually of Rank 6 or 
            higher) to  temporarily  increase your rank for a predetermined 
            amount of time  - until the end of a battle, campaign, or the like. To 
            keep a brevet rank, you must meet the requirements of that rank as 
            well as pay the point cost  (see p. 81). 
            In some armies, rank may be purchased for money. In such a 
            case, a PC who is Wealthy or better gets Rank 3 automatically if 
            desired. Higher levels still cost character points as well as cash. A 
            Wealth level of Average or less doubles the point cost to start with  a 
            Military Rank from 1 to 6. Once a character has been created, rank 
            can be bought for the normal  point  cost, if the  cash  cost for the 
            campaign is met.  
            In many lands, Military Rank carries some automatic Social 
            Status, which need not be paid for separately and has no cash cost 
            to maintain. The "default" here is one level of Status for every 3 of 
            Rank, rounding to the closest number. Where this varies, it will be 
            mentioned in society descriptions. 
            Military Rank is almost always accompanied by a significant 
            Duty (see p. 39). 
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Musical Ability</name>
        <points>1 point/level</points>
        <description>You have a natural talent with music and musical instruments. 
            Your level of musical ability is a bonus when you study Singing or a 
            musical instrument. That is, when you learn a musical ski ll, learn it as 
            though your IQ were equal to (IQ + Musical Ability). This bonus 
            also adds to HT for the Singing skill. Cost: 1 point for each  + 1 
            bonus.  
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Night Vision</name>
        <points>10</points>
        <description>Your eyes adapt rapidly to the darkness. You cannot see in total 
            dark  - but if y ou have  any  light at all, you can see fairly well. 
            Whenever the GM exacts a penalty because of darkness,  except for 
            total darkness, this penalty does not apply to you. 
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Peripheral Vision</name>
        <points>15</points>
        <description>You have an unusually wide field of vision. Whenever some-
            thing dangerous or interesting happens "behind your back," the GM 
            rolls against your IQ. A successful roll means you saw it, or saw 
            enough to alert you in case of an attack. 
            If you are playing with a game map, you can attack into your 
            right and left hexes as well as front hexes. (Note that with a one-
            handed weapon, an attack to the left is clumsy and is still consid-
            ered a "wild swing" - see p. 105.) 
            If you are attacked from the right or left hex, you defend without 
            penalty. Your active defense is at only  -2  against attacks from the rear. 
            You still cannot attack a foe directly behind you (without a wild 
            swing).  
            Furthermore, you have a wider "arc of vision" for ranged 
            attacks. The figure below shows the arc of vision for a normal char-
            acter (white) and for someone with Peripheral Vision (gray plus 
            white). 
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Psionic Resistance</name>
        <points>2 points/level</points>
        <description>Psionic Resistance interferes with  all  uses of psionic powers 
            against you, friendly or hostile, against or  by  the subject. It can 
            never be turned off! 
            If you have Psionic Res istance, the level of your resistance is 
            subtracted from the effective skill of any psionic attempt where you 
            are the subject  - even psychokinesis and clairvoyance. It is also 
            subtracted from your effective skill with any psi ability. Therefore if 
            you have a high Psionic Resistance, it will be hard for you to 
            develop any significant abilities of your own. 
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Rapid Healing</name>
        <points>5</points>
        <description>This advantage is only available if your basic HT is 10 or above. 
            You recover rapidly from all kinds of wounds. Whenever you roll to 
            recover lost HT,  or  when you roll to see if you can get over a 
            crippling injury, add 5 to your effective HT. This ability does not 
            help you get over being stunned, etc. 
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Reputation</name>
        <points>Variable</points>
        <description>A good reputation counts as an advantage. See p. 17.</description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Status</name>
        <points>Variable</points>
        <description>High social status is an advantage. See p. 18. </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Strong Will</name>
        <points>4 points/level</points>
        <description>You have much more "willpower" than the average person. 
            Your level of Will is added to your IQ when you make a Will Roll 
            for any reason, including any attempt to affect you  by Diplomacy, 
            Fast-Talk, Sex Appeal, Interrogation (with or without torture), 
            Hypnotism, or psionic or magical attempts to take over your mind. 
            Strong Will adds to your resistance when you want to resist a magic 
            spell (p. 150). However, this advantage does not help against combat 
            shock, and so on. In questionable cases, the GM's ruling is law. 
            Example: You have 3 levels of Strong Will. An enemy spy is 
            trying to seduce you. The GM rolls a Contest of Skills: the spy's 
            Sex Appeal vs. your IQ. But you have a +3 in the contest, because of 
            your willpower. 
            Cost: 4 points per +1 bonus. 
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Toughness</name>
        <points>10/25 points</points>
        <description>Your skin and flesh are tougher than the average human's. Your 
            body itself has a Damage Resistance score. This DR is treated just 
            like the DR from armor: you subtract it from the damage done by 
            any blow,  before  you multiply the damage done by a cutting or 
            impaling weapon. Toughness does not make you any harder to hit - 
            it just lets you survive more injury.  
            Toughness does not let your  skin "turn" weapons. They still 
            break the skin - they may even draw blood. But you're not hurt.
            However, if a poisoned weapon breaks your skin, the poison will do 
            ts normal damage. Note also that your  eyes  are not tough! A hit 
            here will do normal damage. 
            Cost: 10 points for DR 1, or 25 points for DR 2. Higher bodily 
            DRs are not possible to a "natural" human. But some creatures have 
            natural Toughness, or even natural armor that can stop weapons. 
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Unusual Background</name>
        <points>10 or more points</points>
        <description>This is a "catch-all" advantage that can be used whenever it is 
            needed. For instance, if your parents were traveling merchants, you 
            could reasonably claim to have two or three "native" languages. 
            But that is clearly an unusual background, which costs points. 
            Similarly, if you have access to  skills not available to the people 
            around you, that is Unusual. In general, any time a player comes up 
            with a "character story" that would reasonably give him some special 
            benefit, the GM should  allow this, but require Unusual 
            Background to cover it.  
            The GM may charge extra points if he rules the background is 
            very  unusual. "Raised by aliens" or "trained from birth by a myste-
            rious ninja cult" might be considered "very unusual" in most game-
            worlds. Psi-users, supers or wizards are Very Unusual if they 
            appear in a game world where their special talents are unique. 
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Voice</name>
        <points>10</points>
        <description>You have a naturally clear, resonant and attractive voice. You 
            get a permanent +2 bonus on all the following  skills: Bard, 
            Diplomacy, Performance, Politician, Savoir-Faire, Sex Appeal and 
            Singing. You also get a +2 on any reaction roll made by someone 
            who can hear your voice. 
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Wealth</name>
        <points>Variable </points>
        <description>Wealth can be a truly wonderful advantage. See p. 16 for the 
            point cost for different levels of wealth. Remember that wealth is 
            relative, and determined by the game world you start in. The pre-
            cise meaning of each level will be defined, for each game world, in 
            that world's book.
        </description>
    </advantage>
        
    <advantage>
        <name>Ally</name>
        <points>Variable</points>
        <description>  
            Many fictional heroes have partners  - loyal comrades, faithful 
            sidekicks or life-long friends - who accomp any them on adventures. 
            These partners are Allies. Having an Ally is an advantage. 
            In one sense, the other PCs who adventure with you are allies. 
            But they can be unreliable allies indeed. Often they are chance 
            acquaintances, first encountered at a roadside tavern only hours 
            ago. They have their own hidden goals, ethics and motives, which 
            may or may not coincide with your own. 
            An NPC Ally, on the other hand, is wholly reliable. Perhaps you 
            fought side-by-side in an extended campaign, trained under the 
            same master, or grew up in the same village. The two of you trust 
            each other implicitly. You travel together, fight back-to-back, share 
            rations in hard times, trade watches through the night.  
            The point cost for an Ally is determined by his point value and 
            frequency of appearance.
            An Ally built on 76 to 100 points costs 5 points. 
            An Ally built on 101 to 150 points costs 10 points. 
            An Ally built on 151 to 200 points costs 15 points, etc. 
            An Ally built on over 50 points more than his PC is actually a 
            Patron (p. 24). 
            An Ally having special abilities  - magic powers in a non-magical 
            world, equipment far beyond the world's TL - costs an extra 5 to 10 
            points, at the GM's discretion. 
        </description>
    </advantage>
</advantages>